Hey guys, Shan this side. Welcome back
to the channel and today we are going to
cover one of the very important topic of
micros service that is API gateway. So
let's start without wasting any time. So
what this feature provides? It provides
a single entry point to access all
microser. So let's say you have one
client and if you are working in a
product based company or any company you
know that there is not like only one
client there might be hundreds of
clients okay and you have multiple
microservices like invoice microser
order microser sales microser and also
there are hundreds of microservices in a
very big companies. Okay. So
what happen is API gateway provide a
single entry point. So API gateway sit
between your client and your
microservices and all the calls pass
through this API gateway. So your client
never directly talk with your micros
service. All the clients call pass
through the API gateway. So that's what
it means single entry point. Okay. And
why this exact position of API gateway
make it so important? Because lot of
benefits get added. So one of the
important benefit is routing means it
forward request to write micros service.
So assume this that
client just invoking hey invoke this
API.
Now client doesn't need to know about
all 100 microservices right it doesn't
have to configure that hey for invoice
this is the host and this is the port
for order this is the host and this is
the port so it doesn't need to maintain
that all different clients all 100
clients all need to maintain that okay
this is my source of truth API gateway
only one server internally server does
the routing okay you client you want to
hit / API/ invoice pass the request to
the invoice microser pass the request to
the order microser pass the request to
the sales microser respectively
another is load balancing okay so even
you have multiple
instances of invoice microser so API
gateway can also take care of load
balancing so that when it forward the
request to the particular microser it is
according to the properly load balancing
algorithm
authentication like JWT. So whenever any
request comes in API gateway also have
the capability to do authentication. So
no need to have authentication here.
Authentication and order service
authentication is sales service. You
don't need code duplicacy. Okay. So we
can put the authentication logic at the
API gate gateway itself.
Okay. So because it is act as a first
entry point then your rate limiting
like we can put a rate limit here like
on each microservices itself. So API
gateway also provide that feature
because API gateway is the one which
will always forward the request to a
particular microser right. So we can put
a rate limit here itself. Okay. So that
we can avoid flooding our micros
service. So we will stop the traffic at
the front gate itself.
Resilience circuit breaker retry all
these features API gateway is capable of
request response transformation. So what
the request is coming it can do some
transformation and whatever the response
it we are returning from the microser
API gateway intercepted do some changes
and then can return to the client that
is also possible monitoring and logging.
So for each request which is coming we
can put a centralized log here also that
is also possible. So we will see
everything like how we can achieve this
through Microsoft uh API gateway. Okay.
So first thing first
routing forward request to a right
microser. So assume this I have already
explained. So we can have multiple
clients we can have multiple
microservices all running on different
ports. Okay. So and it is possible that
in future one microser is divided into
multiple or multiple microser merge
together. So this is keep on going in a
world of microservices. This is keep on
going. You can add new microser or even
for one microser if this become huge it
breaks into smaller smaller
microservices further.
So if clients are directly interacting
with the microservices and if there is
any change then all clients need to
update the routing logic. Okay. Now
let's say that in this example order
microservices is gone. It's merged with
your sale microser. Now this microser
order and sale microser. So all this 100
client need to update the routing logic.
Earlier they whatever the traffic they
are passing it to here now they have to
pass it to this one. So it impact is
huge and because of that
the decision of creation merging it's
not easy
but with API gateway in mid the clients
are not even bothered about it they only
talk with API gateway now only API
gateway we need to update the routing
logic okay if this is the API earlier it
was passing to here now it knows that it
need to pass to this new microser.
Okay. So only one application is changed
not hundreds.
Okay.
So let's implement this. What we are
going to implement? So we are creating
two microser product microser order
micros service. Okay. And we are going
to create an API gateway service. Now
whenever any request comes so our client
would be here postman
from postman when we invoke slash
product
let's say / id1.
So API gateway should intercept it and
decide okay any request which is
starting with / products I need to
forward it to product micros service and
the second is let's say if client calls
orders
/ one something now it intercept that
any API starts with / order I need to
pass it order microser
so this we have to implement it now
So first thing products product
microservices you can goes to spring
initializer okay just java you can
select the latest version java 17 java
21 whichever you want to work with and
normal spring web normal application
okay so once you done that we can have
one rest controller where we are just
exposed one endpoint / products slash id
like / product one whatever the client
will pass and it will just returning
fetch the product details with id that's
all nothing else okay and we are running
this application on port number 8082
so our product setup is complete order
microservices is also very simple create
a new micros service give it a name
order like is spring web just we need
this uh dependency and just create a
very basic controller /order/ / id we
will expose one endpoint and we will
just print f the order details with id
this one that's all nothing else and the
port number on which we are running the
order is 80081
so this is also run it is running on
8081 and this is on 8082 so this is also
setup completed
now we need to set up
gateway so on the spring initializer you
can choose java maven one the version
give the name API gateway jar Java 17
whichever we are running now we have to
choose this dependency reactive gateway
okay so what it will do is it will bring
this dependency into our pom doxml
spring cloud starter gateway so this
dependency will get added because of
this when we add into spring initializer
through UI
so this is the first thing So now our
dependency is present. Now in
application.property
of this project API gateway.
First thing is we are running it on port
number 8083.
Okay. Now
we are adding the routing logic. So I
have added two routing logic. Why two?
One is for product, another is for
order. Okay. Okay. And this is running
on 8083 port number. So let's add a
product
routing logic. So see this one
configuration is like spring
dotcloud.gateway
route zero. So it is like we can gateway
is might be connecting to multiple
microservices like product like order
like sales like payment multiple. So
it's like
route 01. It's like an array. You can
consider it as an array. So route zero
is for product. Route one is for order.
Similarly, if there are more, route two
is maybe for your sales. Then route four
maybe you are for payment. Likewise.
Okay. So route zero dot id. So this is
any unique name we can provide. So I'm
just giving product service. You can
give any name in this one.
Okay. The second is route0. URI. So this
is the URI
for this microservices.
So let's say API gateway is forwarding
to this microser. It is like running on
localhost
8082.
So that's what I am passing it here
http localhost 8082 where this microser
is running host and port.
Now the third one is route zero
predicates zero. So predicate is also an
array. There can be multiple predicates.
Okay. So predicate 0, predicate 1,
predicate 2, there can be multiple
predicates also. Predicate considered as
a filter.
Okay. So the first filter which I am
putting is path equals to /rouct/star
star means any traffic which start with
/ products I need to forward it to this
path
this URI.
Okay. So you can have more you can add
more predicates. So let's say I am
adding this spring.cloud.gateway.troo0.
Route0 means this product one. So route
0 route zero this one. So we are in the
0 one we are adding for product service.
So route 0 dot predicate one. So
predicate is also an array right in the
zeroth one I added for path. In the
predicate one I added for method. So
equals to method
is allowed only get post. So what now it
will match any API which start with /
product star or any API start with this
after this it we can have anything okay
but any API which start with / products
but it should be get and post then we
will a root matching will success and it
will pass to this URL
okay
so this is just an example but uh In the
application.properties, I have only one
predicate or one filter that is for
path. So whenever we will hit through
our postman
/ product/
let's say id anything it will pass it to
this product microser no matter it's a
get or put or post or delete because we
have only one predicate
not many. Similarly for order you can
also define first is now spring.cloud
Cloud gateway route one. So now one is
our our order. So you can give any
unique ID then provide a URI what is the
microser order microservices located at
your host and port number and the
filters. So route one which is for order
and predicate zero then you can have
predicates one two likewise. So
currently we have only one predicate
which is based on path. So path equals
to any API which start with or
then pass it to this URI. So you can
have like method. So here we have like
method. Then also you can have header.
There are I think four five predicates
we can use that but
these are the most important use path
and method. Generally method also is not
heavily used. path is the one which is
very frequently used like if this path
match
pass it to
this specific service.
Okay.
So we have added the routing
and now let's start all the three
servers. So my product service is
running on 80082. My order service is
running on 8081 and my API gateway is
running on 8083. So now all three
servers are started.
Now from the client which is now our
postman
I am not calling here if you see
localhost 8083 I am calling. I am not
calling product endpoint product is
running on 8082
but here if you see I am calling 8083. I
am hitting API gateway where my API
gateway is running.
So now I pass /roucts /1.
So what it will do? It will do a
matching.
So any API started with / products, it
will pass it to product endpoint and it
will fetch the product details with ID
1. This is what the controller we have
added.
F the product with ID.
If it is an order, it will pass it API
gateway pass it to proper order service
and it will able to invoke this endpoint
f the order details with id. So now here
I am calling same API gateway endpoint
/1. So it will
properly forward the request to the
order micros service f the order details
with id1. So properly it invoked the
order service.
Okay.
So one thing you might be thinking hey
Shange
you have hardcoded the URI here.
Okay. Means it will always forward the
request to a particular microser. What
if we have multiple instances of a
microser? It's possible right? So our
second thing second benefit of API
gateway comes into the picture which is
load balancer. Okay. So we can have
multiple instances of product, right? So
this is instance one. Then we have
instance two. We can have instance
three, instance four, multiple
instances. Okay.
Now this API gateway should also perform
load balancing. So if you know we have
already covered service discovery and
the client side load balancer. So that
comes into the picture. If you haven't
seen these two videos, uh I would highly
recommend kindly check this out because
in this one we have internally discussed
how client side load balancer works, how
service discovery works because now API
gateway make use of this since there are
multiple instances present
that's where we need service discovery
because now API gateway need to know
that what are the instances present
let's say for product instance one is
running on this host and this port.
Instance two is running on this host
this port. Okay. Similarly for order
these are the list host and port for
each instances. So who will provide this
list? Service discovery. Okay. So that's
why we need to integrate with service
discovery and after this we have to do a
load balancing and for that we will use
a spring load balancer. Spring crowd
load balancer which does client side
load balancing
framework is going to same the
internally API gateway itself use the
same framework. So internally whatever
the internal framework we saw right how
the client side load balancer works that
going to be same so no changing in that
one. So now product service now we have
to integrate with service discovery
right. the product service. So now you
know if you have seen the service
discovery you know this is our server
this is our client this is our client
this is our client okay
so the product service we have added as
a ureka client okay and in the
application.properties properties we
have
put the path of the ureka. So now with
this one it will tell any instance of a
product service is created it will
register itself with the service
discovery also we have already discussed
that in the service discovery video.
Similarly for the order we have make it
a client ureka client and in the
application.properties
we have provided a link for the ureka uh
service server. Okay.
And we already have this controller same
like previously we have. So no change
into that one. So now this become my
client uh Ureka client. This is Ureka
client. Ureka server. So this is our
service discovery server. So we have
added a dependency ureka server. In the
application.properties
we put the endpoint on which it is
running 8761.
and we make it these two things false.
I've already shared in the service
discovery video what its purpose. So I'm
not going to uh again going into that
but if you see if you have any doubt
with service discovery I would highly
recommend again check this out. Okay. So
I created the service discovery server.
Now API gateway. So till now what I have
done is I have set up my product
service. I have set up my order
microser. I have set up my Ureka server.
Now API gateway whatever I have now I
need to make it
client also ureka client. So API gateway
we already have this dependency spring
cloud gateway starter gateway. Now I
added as a ureka client dependency also.
Okay. And in application.property
property.
We already have this route one for route
zero for product, route one for order.
Now I have added the Ureka server on
which server on which URI URA server is
running. Okay. So that is also done. Now
here if you see one difference is in the
product route and order route in the URI
instead of hard coding the URI http
localhost 8082
and here 8081 something I put lb colon
and give the
service name which they have registered
with the ureka server. Okay. So they are
registered with this order service
product service with this name. It will
get registered to this service
discovery. Okay. So I provided this name
load balancer order service.
Now what it will do is internally it
will make use of spring cloud load
balancer.
Okay. So it will fetch the instances. So
first it will fetch the instances from
service discovery. Now service discovery
will give you the all the possible
instances present for a product or order
and after that it will perform load
balancing algorithm and it will pick one
it will pick one instance and call the
particular instance.
So these two videos you can say that you
need to know how the internals client
side load balancer working so that you
can uh easily understand what I did
here.
Okay.
So we
our API gateway is able to do load
balancing also through spring cloud load
balancer.
All we need to do is integrate with the
service discovery.
Okay. And we just enable the Spring
Cloud load balancer. Through this, it
will intercept the request, call the
service discovery first, fetch fetches
the instance and then do a load
balancing algorithm and call one
particular instance.
Okay. So you can uh so I will also share
the repo with you uh git link gitlab
link with where we have all this code
present. Okay. So I have an API gateway
which is running
which is running then I have ureka
server
okay so in ureka server we have it is
running on 8761 then I have order
service then product service so all are
running so if you try to hit let's say
80083 is our API gateway run right API
gateway but I am calling orders one if
it call it's running so currently My
product service is not running. So let
me start its application.
So my product application is also
running now on 8082. So now lets
product /1
it's product or products
products
f the product details with ID1. So even
though I'm hitting API gateway so I will
share the GitLab link also where I have
provided all the links all the code. Now
the next part in the next API gateway
part where we will see the
authentication
rate limiting uh resilience circuit
breaker retry and everything how the API
gateway
handles that that is also very important
part right. So today at least in the
first basic part we know how API gateway
route the logic plus does load
balancing. If you have any doubt with
this one we can discuss further in the
comment section. Okay guys, thank you.
Bye.